Next, move on to look at the back of the eye.
Hold the ophthalmoscope in your right hand to examine the right eye and vice versa.
Start with your feet close to the patient and lean back.
Ask the patient to fix on a specific distance target on
the horizontal and avoid looking at the light of the ophthalmoscope.
Slowly start to move in from 10 to 15 degrees temporal on the horizontal meridian with zero power lens.
Keep the red reflex in view and move closer to the patient.
The optic disc should come into view when you refuse to
centimeters away.
Comment on how distinctive the margin of the disc is, the
color of the neuro-retinal rim and cup to disc ratio.
If you cannot see the disc,
then move in the direction that the branches of the retinal vessel's point.
This will guide you towards the disc.
In this examination the optic nerve is
swollen.
The margin is indistinct and the central cup is absent due to being
filled by the surrounding swollen nerve.
The fine capillaries on the surface of
the nerve that obscured, as are some of the large arterials.
The veins are swollen and
there is a small hemorrhage present at 9 o'clock.
These signs are all consistent with papillodema
due to raised intracranial pressure.
This optic nerve has a much more distinct margin,
but the neuroretinal rim is diffusely pale.
This is the appearance of optocatrophe.
In this
examination the central cup is enlarged with thinning of the neuroretinal rim.
The nerve
Consequently has an enlarged cup to disc ratio of 0.8, highly suggestive of the presence of
glaucoma.